<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians race teaching vs all so worthily, and so wisely both to beginne, continue, and to end, this our most short and momentanie [sic] course in this mortall life: that in the day of our death wee may for euer enjoy that inestimable crowne of eternall blisse in the life to come. Being a sermon preached in the Parish Church of North Parrott in Somerset, by Iohn Atkins Master of Arts, and preacher of the sacred Word of God, and pastor there.</title>
            <author>Atkins, John, Rector of North Parrott.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850596</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15807</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22452)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15807)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 910:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians race teaching vs all so worthily, and so wisely both to beginne, continue, and to end, this our most short and momentanie [sic] course in this mortall life: that in the day of our death wee may for euer enjoy that inestimable crowne of eternall blisse in the life to come. Being a sermon preached in the Parish Church of North Parrott in Somerset, by Iohn Atkins Master of Arts, and preacher of the sacred Word of God, and pastor there.</title>
                  <author>Atkins, John, Rector of North Parrott.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Stansby] for George Hodges, and are to bee sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Gray-hound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ (-F4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:1"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS RACE: TEACHING VS ALL SO WORTHILY, AND SO WISELY Both to beginne, continue, and to end, this our moſt <hi>ſhort and momentanie courſe in this mortall Life: that in</hi> the day of our death wee may for euer enjoy that ineſtimable Crowne of eternall Bliſſe <hi>in the life to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being a Sermon preached in the Pariſh Church of <hi>North Parrott</hi> in <hi>Somerſet,</hi> by IOHN ATKINS Maſter of Arts, and Preacher of the ſacred Word of God, and Paſtor <hi>there.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. COR. 9.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Know yee not that they which runne in a Race runne all, but one receiued the price? So runne that yee may obtayne.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>George Hodges,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Gray-hound. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM SAINTMAVRE, LORD BEAVCHAMPE, EARLE OF <hi>HERTFORD:</hi> AND TO THE MOST Vertuous and truly Religious Counteſſe; my very good Lord and Ladie, IOHN ATKINS wiſheth all grace, and peace from our LORD IESVS <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vſtome (which with vs is another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) hath euermore claymed by Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription (Right Honourable) that ſuch Bookes, as are publikely committed to the Preſſe, whither they bee ſmall or great, ſhould be ſent abroad to the open view of the World, with ſome Epiſtle Dedicatorie going before them. Which if they haue not, they may then bee queſtioned by the Readers, whither that the Authors and Writers of theſe Works, haue any worthy good Friends abroad: or elſe, whither that the Workes themſelues may be thought well worthy of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage.
<pb facs="tcp:15807:3"/>In due regard whereof, I haue here in bent my ſelfe to tread the common path, and now at this preſent to vſher forth into the Vineyard of Gods Church, theſe firſt Fruits of mine imprinted labours in my publike Miniſterie, vnder both your Honours moſt worthy Patronage (which are now but one in the Lord.) Moſt humbly crauing your Honours fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable acceptance of the fame, <hi>as our Sauiour once did of that poore Widdowes Farthing.</hi> And although I may moſt truly confeſſe and ſay, in the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, of that <hi>Centurion</hi> in the Goſpell, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.8. I am not worthy to bee graced here in by your Honours greatneſſe (knowing right well mine owne vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) yet the very little matter, and argument it ſelfe, of this little Booke of mine is it, which I haue heere made bold to commend vnto you, to wit, <hi>The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Race:</hi> A Race indeed, which the Wiſemen of this World doe vtterly refuſe to runne, becauſe they are yet but Worldly wiſe: and what our ignorant ones dreame not of, becauſe that their eyes as yet are blinded: and what our Naturaliſts know not of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that this Race is ſpiritually diſcerned, and what our Earth-wormes thinke not of, becauſe that all ſuch are but earthly minded: and which all our prophane ones vtterly deſpiſe, becauſe that as yet they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together irreligious: and which all our vngodly ones as yet regard not, becauſe that their hearts are hard and ſtony, and which our Hypocrites know right wel, but yet will not runne, vnleſſe it be only in the ſight of men for a ſeaſon, to haue the applauſe and prayſe of men: and laſtly, which all our truly Religious ones ſtriue to runne; albeit, with many faintings, failings,
<pb facs="tcp:15807:3"/>and deſertions. And therefore (now Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to this only end, that all our Worldly wiſe <hi>(bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dictione diuina)</hi> may be yet more truly wiſe vnto their owne ſaluation: and all our ignorant ones may be the more enlightned, and all our Naturaliſts may bee the more renewed, and all our Worldly ones may the more haue their minds ſet on heauenly things, and all our prophane ones may yet proue the more pious, and all our vngodly ones may come at laſt to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: and all our Hypocrites may be much more zealous, ſo many as are found within the ranke of Election. And finally, all our Religious ones may be much more ſtrengthened, and animated in that good courſe which they haue hither vnto begunne, that ſo conſtantly and comfortably continuing to the Goales end, they may reape that rich price of eternall bliſſe.</p>
            <p>I haue heere made bold for the publike good of Gods Church, to commit this ſhort Sermon of mine to the Preſſe: teaching both your Honours in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and all true Chriſtians elſe in generall, ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne, hold on, and continue this our true Chriſtian Race, vnto the very end and vpſhot of our liues: that in death we may enioy eternall life.</p>
            <p>Vouchſafe therefore (Right Honourable, I beſeech you) to permit this little Worke of mine, to paſſe into the World vnder your Honours Name, which in truth will not only be euen as a ſhield to protect it againſt the bitter and biting Tongues of all our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and captious Ones, but alſo bee as an Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment powred out, yeelding a moſt ſweete and redo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſauour, for to make it ſo much the more odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb facs="tcp:15807:4"/>indeed, in the hearts and minds of all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Readers, and Hearers of the ſame. And thus moſt humbly crauing pardon for this my boldneſſe, and not being willing to detayne your Honours any longer, leaſt I ſhould be too tedious. I commend you and yours to that moſt gracious God, whom you daily ſerue, and to the Word of his grace, which is able to build further in you both, and to giue you an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all them that are ſatisfied.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours Chaplaine in all</hi> dutie to be commanded, IOHN ATKINS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader: foraſmuch as wee are all (as Experience proueth, the ſureſt Schoole-miſtreſſe in the world) from the King to the Begger: from the best to the baſeſt: from the mightieſt to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt: from him that ſits vpon the Throne: to the pooreſt grinder in the Mill, without exception, or exemption of any. Actors heere vpon the Stage of no long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: and (as euidently the Holy Ghoſt doth witneſſe vnto vs all, in the <hi>1. Cor. 9.24.</hi>) runners of a most ſhort and tranſitorie race heere in this mortall life: the which race being finiſhed first, or laſt: either at our firſt, third, ſixth, or eleuenth houre. That is to ſay, either in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, Youth, Middle age, or Old age: our Bodies muſt then returne vnto Duſt, from whence they came: and our Soules muſt returne vnto <hi>GOD</hi> who gaue them. That therefore in the very day and houre of our Deaths: that immortall part, I meane our ſoules, (which as Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaith, <hi>Generando infunduntur &amp; infundendo generantur,</hi> are infuſed into our bodyes by a Diuine and vnvtterable generation, and are begotten of <hi>GOD</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in vs, by a Coeleſtiall infuſion,) may not bee repulſed by <hi>CHRIST</hi> himſelfe, the Iudge of quicke and dead, with <hi>Non noui vos, diſcedite maledicti, &amp;c.</hi> I know you
<pb facs="tcp:15807:5"/>not, depart you Curſed, &amp;c. But may then bee immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, and that most ioyfully admitted, into the <hi>Coelum Emperaeum,</hi> the Heauen of Heauens, with that ſweet <hi>Venite benidicti, &amp;c.</hi> Come yee bleſſed Children of my Father, &amp;c. to <hi>GODS</hi> moſt comfortable preſence, there to haue full fellowſhip with the Bleſſed Trinitie, and with all the Communion of the tryumphant Saints, and ſo raigne with them in Bliſſe for euermore. I haue heere made bold in loue, as <hi>GODS</hi> poore Labourer (though <hi>Apoſtolorum minimus, Peccatorum maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; Sanctorum infimus:</hi> the leaſt of the Apoſtles, named of <hi>GOD,</hi> chiefest Sinner, and the meaneſt Saint.) to commend this compendious Sermon of mine vnto thy Chriſtian view, for thy better inſtruction and daily direction in this preſent Life (which is but for a moment) how to runne moſt wiſely and worthily indeed, of this thine appointed Spirituall race. The which poore Mite of mine, if I ſhall finde thee (courteous Reader) with wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe and chearefulneſſe to accept, and with careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and faithfulneſſe daily for to vſe, it ſhall then bee thine; Otherwiſe, if you doe graceleſly abuſe it, or elſe most groſſely refuſe it, then it ſhall bee mine. Reade, and conſider well I pray thee with good diſcretion, what heere thou readeſt: and the Lord giue vs all a right vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all good things. And if vpon thy reading, or hearing hereof, you ſhall finde any Spirituall and Ghoſtly comfort for to follow: let <hi>GOD</hi> haue all the glorie, to whom all Glorie chiefly appertayneth: and let mee (the Lords vnworthy Minister) haue thy daily Prayers to <hi>GOD</hi> in my behalfe, that <hi>GOD</hi> of his goodneſſe may ſo bleſſe me in my Miniſtrie, which I haue receiued from the Lord, as that hereby I may from henceforth be boldly
<pb facs="tcp:15807:5"/>encouraged, and enabled to prepare yet ſome few Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations more of this kinde hereafter for thee. And thus most heartily commending it to thy Chriſtian and charitable conſideration, and my ſelfe with all my daily Studies and endeauours, vnto thy most faithfull and feruent prayers, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Ieſus. IOHN ATKINS.</signed>
               <dateline>North <hi>Parrot</hi> in <hi>Somerſet,</hi> 
                  <date>this twelfth of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>1623.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="doctrines">
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:6"/>
            <head>Fiue generall Doctrines, or Inſtructions, handled in this <hi>Sermon.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <label>Firſt, <hi>from the word,</hi> Vs.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>THat all the Elect of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Doctrine.</note> 
                  <hi>which doe expect indeed, that rich reward of Glory in the day of Death: must labour now to be</hi> Curſores, <hi>Spirituall runners of the Christians race, heere in this preſent Life.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Secondly, <hi>from the word,</hi> Runne.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That all thoſe which are ſound profeſſours indeed of true Christian Religion:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Doctrine.</note> 
                  <hi>must neither ſtand ſtill nor ſit downe, nor flinch, nor looke backe, but daily goe forward in this Religious race, vntill they come in Death vnto that wiſhed place.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Thirdly, <hi>from the word,</hi> Race.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That mans life heere vpon Earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Doctrine.</note> 
                  <hi>it is exceeding ſhort, and paſſeth very ſwiftly.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Fourthly, <hi>from the word,</hi> Patience.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That true Patience indeed in vndergoing of Croſſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Doctrine.</note> is a moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and gainefull Grace, for the fitting, fencing, and furniſhing of our Soules, to runne this Religious race.</item>
               <label>Fiftly, <hi>from theſe words:</hi> Looking to IESVS.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>That in running of this our Religious race,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Doctrine.</note> 
                  <hi>the life of our Lord and Maſter</hi> Ieſus, <hi>muſt bee our ſpeciall Card and Compaſſe, our Coeleſtiall Circle, and our Line, for to guide vs by.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:6"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIANS RACE.</head>
            <head type="sub">THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Heb. <hi>12. Part of the 1. &amp; 10. Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let vs runne with Patience the Race that is ſet before vs, looking vnto <hi>IESVS.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe words (my welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in CHRIST IESVS, our beſt beloued:) the Holy Ghoſt <hi>(our coeleſtiall Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter of all true ſauing Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge)</hi> doth borrow a very plaine and familiar compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as wee may all perceiue and ſee) from the Earthly games of mortall Men, which in a word, wee may thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. The Race which we are heere exhorted for to runne, is not the voluptuous Race of vaine pleaſure with <hi>Epicurus: (whoſe wanton Song was onely thus:</hi> Ede, bibe, lude: poſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem nulla voluptas. <hi>Eate, drinke, and play: for after death there
<pb facs="tcp:15807:7"/>is no further pleaſure:</hi>) Nor yet the ambitious Race of vaine Glory, with <hi>Alexander:</hi> who hauing Conquered all this World, wept becauſe hee could not finde a ſecond: that ſo he might alſo conquer it: Nor yet the enuious Race of beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like reuenge, with that accurſed <hi>Caine,</hi> who moſt inſatiably thirſted after his Brother <hi>Abels</hi> innocent blood. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.8. Nor yet the couetous Race of this worlds bewitching wealth: with that moſt greedie Cormorant mentioned in the Goſpell: (<hi>Luk.</hi> 12.18.19. <hi>Qui modo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lligat hordeum in horreum, &amp;c.</hi> ſo as hee might fill his Barnes vp to the roofe:) This was the whole and ſole compaſſe of his cares: being crop-ſicke (as I may ſay) out of his great abundance. But onely that pious and Religious race, of a new, a holy, a godly, and a ſanctified life, with that regenerate and moſt worthy King <hi>Dauid:</hi> running in the path of Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.32. <hi>Let vs runne with patience this race that is ſet before vs, looking to Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which words, that I may the more orderly ſpeake, and you in Gods feare the more profitably heare: may it pleaſe you all, for methods ſake (which is memories guide,) ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to obſerue herein theſe two generall and remarkeable parts; to wit, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the parties that are heere exhorted for to runne this Religious race: in the firſt particle <hi>Vs:</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, there manner of practice in running of the ſame: which is, <hi>To runne with patience the race that is ſet before vs, looking to Ieſus.</hi> The parties, are not all men in generall, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, but onely <hi>Vs:</hi> that is, all the righteous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate ranke, which being made Spiritually new creatures in Chriſt Ieſus, are Iuſtified by the merit of Chriſt his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Sanctified by his moſt bleſſed Word and Spirit. And ſo this word <hi>Vs,</hi> hath onely a reference to all that are of this righteous and regenerate ranke, whither <hi>Iewes,</hi> or <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> male, or female, noble, or ignoble, learned, or vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, bond, or free. So that in this ſence (as you may perceiue and ſee) the perſons are not definitely, but indefinitely heere propoſed. For the Holy Ghoſt doth not ſay heere: Let vs
<pb facs="tcp:15807:7"/>that are Noble, or let vs that are Ignoble, or let vs that are Mightie, or let vs that are Meane, or let vs that are Rich, or let vs that are Poore, or let vs that are Young, or let vs that are Old: but generally (hauing a reſpect to all the regenerate onely) hee expreſſeth it indefinte in this wiſe: <hi>Let vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> And hence <hi>à perſonis</hi> from the parties, heere moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exhorted, for to runne this Religious race, there ariſeth this obſeruable leſſon for our further Learning, that all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of GOD, which doe expect indeed, that rich reward of Glorie in their day of Death: muſt belabour <hi>now to bee Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores,</hi> Spirituall runners of the Chriſtians race, heere in this preſent life. The reaſon is drawne <hi>à decreto Dei:</hi> becauſe that the Lord himſelfe hath ſo Decreed: That firſt, we muſt bee all of vs <hi>Viatores,</hi> Trauellers, and <hi>Curſores,</hi> Runners, ere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that we can be <hi>Comprehenſores,</hi> obtainers of eternall Life. Inſomuch, that in this reſpect, not the very true naturall Sonne of God himſelfe, as hee was the very Sonne of Man, (like vnto vs in all things excepting onely in ſinne) was in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe exempted, or priuiledged aboue his Brethren, whiles that hee was heere militant, and conuerſant vpon Earth. But firſt he did Runne, and then after that Obtayne: firſt hee did Fight, and then he did Conquer: firſt he did Suffer, and then after that hee did enter into his Glorie. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.26. So then (my welbeloued in the beſt beloued) this being the Militant eſtate heere vpon Earth of Chriſt himſelfe our head: this alſo muſt bee the Lot, Eſtate, and Condition, of all and euery one of vs, that are his members. For that as in <hi>Math.</hi> 10.25. wee may runne, and read, from the mouth of our Maſter Chriſt himſelfe: It is enough for the Diſciple to be as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and the Seruant as his Lord. And no maruel; for, as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Father ſaith. Our God hath theſe three diſtinct or ſeueral houſes: Earth, Hell, and Heauen: Earth for labour, Hell for torment, and Heauen for pleaſure: Earth for labour in this preſent life; whereof that holy man <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh thus, in <hi>Iob</hi> 5.7. Man is borne to labour, as the ſparkes to flie vpward. Hell, for torment to all the Damned, in the life to come:
<pb facs="tcp:15807:8"/>whereof <hi>Abraham</hi> ſpake thus to damned <hi>Diues,</hi> in <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.25. Sonne remember that thou in thy life time receiuedſt thy pleaſures, and contrariwiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> endured paines: but now hee is comforted, and thou art tormented. And Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for pleaſure, to all the Elect of God, whereof our bleſſed Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writeth thus, in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. That no Eye euer ſaw, no Eare euer heard, no Heart euer conceiued, the joyes which God hath prepared <hi>in Coelo Empiraeo,</hi> for them that loue him. So then, if heere wee haue no fighting, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, running, encountring, and conquering in this preſent life: we can neuer then looke for any Coeleſtiall bleſſing, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Crowning, and moſt happie rewarding in the Life to come. And therefore of force I muſt thus conclude, <hi>à de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto Dei immutabili,</hi> from Gods vnchangeable Decree, the truth of this my propoſed Doctrine raiſed <hi>a perſonis,</hi> from the perſons, which are heere exhorted by the Holy Ghoſt, for to runne this <hi>Chriſtian race,</hi> that if euer wee doe expect indeed, that rich reward of Glorie in the day of our Death: wee muſt labour now with might and maine, for to bee <hi>Curſores,</hi> Spirituall runners of this Religious race heere in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this Doctrine <hi>a Perſonis,</hi> from the Perſons, ſerues to reprooue, to checke, and ſharpely to rebuke, many thouſands amongſt vs in theſe our dayes and times, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet but <hi>Talpae in Diuinis,</hi> blind Moales in Heauenly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, doe ignorantly, and moſt abſurdly thinke to goe to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as it were vpon beds of Downe, and that all other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and buſineſſes in this world, this one thing is the eaſieſt matter of all, for a man to enter into Eternall life, in his day of Death: and in this Life to bee ſpiritually rich towards God, with a Lord haue mercy vpon them at the laſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (<hi>lumine Naturae</hi> by Natures light,) they can all confeſſe and ſay; that a man cannot poſſibly bee rich to this ſlipperie world, firſt beginning euen <hi>ex nihilo,</hi> but of a ſlender Stocke: without riſing vp early, &amp; going to bed late, and taking of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opportunitie offered for that end and purpoſe: and yet alas
<pb facs="tcp:15807:8"/>theſe Naturaliſts doe thinke, (being yet but fleſh and bloud) which as our Apoſtle plainly tels vs from the Lord, in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 50. cannot poſſibly enter into the Kingdome of God) to be ſpirituall rich to God-ward in their ſoules: and ſuddenly, <hi>in ipſo articulo mortis;</hi> at the very laſt gaſpe, to enjoy CHRIST, with all his Merits, Graces, and Bleſſings (which is mans beſt and chiefeſt gaine, becauſe the moſt true and perfect gaine:) though heere they doe ſtand ſtill in the way of ſinners, or ſit downe in the ſeate of the ſcornfull: neuer running (as we are here exhorted) in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Race; nor yet ſtrugling, or ſtriuing, as Chriſtians ought to doe; either againſt Satans fiery ſuggeſtions, or againſt this Worlds moſt dangerous hallucinations, or againſt their owne carnall luſts and moſt filthy corruptions: but that only one, <hi>Miſerere mei Deus,</hi> at the laſt, will ſuffice their turne.</p>
            <p>To all which blind Moales in heauenly matters, I muſt be a ghoſtly Remembrancer this day from the Lord of Heauen and Earth, with this my preſent Doctrine, raiſed <hi>à perſonis,</hi> from the parties, which muſt runne this our Chriſtians Race. That if euer they doe expect indeed, that moſt rich reward of glory in the day of death: they muſt labour now then to bee <hi>curſores,</hi> ſpirituall runners of this Religious Race here in this preſent life. Remembring ſtill, that as a godly Father ſayth: <hi>Nunc pugnandum tibi eſt fortiter, nunc currendum viriliter: vt tandem in die mortis triumphes ſuauiter.</hi> Now wee muſt fight couragiouſly, now wee muſt runne manfully: if euer wee looke in our day of death to triumph moſt ioyfully. And ſo I come, <hi>à perſonis ad rem,</hi> from the parties that muſt runne this Religious Race, to their practice in running and finiſhing of the ſame: which is, <hi>To runne with patience the Race that is ſet before vs, looking to Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which two generall parts of this my propoſed Text, may it pleaſe you methodically to note theſe three particular points. Firſt, A word of Exhortation in that firſt word <hi>Run.</hi> Secondly, A moſt worthy direction how, in theſe next words: <hi>with patience the Race that is ſet before vs.</hi> And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:15807:9"/>and laſtly: An illuſtration of this moſt worthy direction, by a demonſtration drawne, <hi>ab exemplo Chriſti:</hi> in theſe laſt words, <hi>looking to Ieſus.</hi> Of theſe (by the helpe of God) in their order. And firſt, of the word of Exhortation, <hi>Runne.</hi> Running (as wee all know) is a violent exerciſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt painfull and laborious: And ſo likewiſe is the mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant preſent eſtate of euery man and woman amongſt vs, that will runne this Chriſtians Race full of affliction, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and of trouble: inſomuch, that <hi>Sicut fluctus fluctum inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur: ſic afflictio afflictionem:</hi> as one waue followeth vpon the Seas, in the necke of another: ſo doe tryals and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here purſue Gods deare Saints one after another. And therefore, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> counſell is this in his ſecond Chapter and firſt Verſe, <hi>My Sonne if thou wilt come to ſerue the Lord, prepare thy ſoule for temptations.</hi> Moreouer, in running, which (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue taught you) is <hi>actio laborioſa:</hi> a violent, painfull, and laborious exerciſe of the bodie: mens bodies are ſtill <hi>in motu, &amp; progreſſu:</hi> in action, and in progreſſe, vntill they doe come at length vnto the Goale.</p>
            <p>And euen ſo likewiſe (my welbeloued in the beſt beloued) both in our ſpeculatiue, and practicall part of true Chriſtian Pietie, our whole man fleſh, and ſpirit muſt ſtill be <hi>in motu &amp; progreſſu:</hi> vntill we doe attayne to that wiſhed Palace of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie. And hence from this firſt word of Exhortation, <hi>Run;</hi> There ariſeth this remarkable Inſtruction, or Leſſon for our learning: that all ſuch, as doe now profeſſe indeed true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Pietie, and Religion; muſt neither ſtand ſtill, nor ſit downe, nor flinch, nor looke backe: but goe on ſtill forward in this ſpirituall Race, till in death they ſhall come vnto their wiſhed place.</p>
            <p>The reaſon for the purpoſe and confirmation of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is drawne <hi>à comparatis,</hi> from a compariſon: becauſe that euen as runners in an Earthly Race, doe not at all, whiles they are Agents in that corporall exerciſe, either ſtand ſtill or ſit downe, or flinch, or looke backe: but doe hold on cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, cheerefully, and conſtantly, vntill they attayne
<pb facs="tcp:15807:9"/>vnto their wiſhed Goale: Euen ſo muſt wee that are now <hi>Curſores,</hi> ſpirituall runners in this our Religious Race: not ſtand ſtill with thoſe Idlers in the Goſpell, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.6. whom our Sauiour himſelfe did moſt ſharpely checke with <hi>Quid hic ſtatis toto die otioſi? Why ſtand yee heere all the day idle?</hi> Nor yet ſit downe with that couetous Cormorant in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. who ſang this ſweete <hi>requiem</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſoule: ſaying, <hi>Anima requieſce: Soule take thy reſt.</hi> Nor yet flinch with thoſe daſtardly Diſciples of our Sauiour, who fled all away from him, at the houre of his apprehenſion, <hi>Mar.</hi> 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> 50. Nor yet laſtly looke backe with that diſobedient Wife of righteous <hi>Lot, Gen.</hi> 19. <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. who was deſeruedly therefore <hi>turned into a Pillar of Salt:</hi> to be a warning peale (as I may ſay) to all ſucceeding Ages. But according to that moſt bleſſed patterne and practice of our holy and bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.13.14. <hi>Wee must forget that which is behind,</hi> that is, <hi>the things we haue alreadie done, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour our ſelues to that which is before:</hi> that is, <hi>to thoſe good duties, which as yet we haue left vndone, and preſſe continually to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the marke, which is our Maſter Ieſus Chriſt alone:</hi> vpon whom, as on a marke, our eyes muſt be wholy and ſolely ſet, in the compleat courſe of this our Chriſtian Race. And albeit in the running of this Race, we may either ſtumble, or fall, or both: as <hi>Dauid</hi> did; when hee committed both Murder and Adulterie, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. and as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did, when he denyed and defied his Lord and Maſter Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.72, 74. and as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, when a pricke was giuen him in the fleſh, the very Meſſenger of Satan to buffet him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. and generally as all the Diſciples did, when as they all forſooke their Maſter Chriſt, and fled, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.56. Yet wee muſt vp againe, and to it; We muſt breake off our wonted ſinnes by righteouſneſſe, and our iniquities by mercifulneſſe. So that if with the Church of <hi>Epheſus, Wee haue left our firſt Loue, Reuel.</hi> 2.5. yet we muſt againe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from whence we are fallen, and repent, and doe our firſt workes. If then in running of this Religious Race wee doe
<pb facs="tcp:15807:10"/>fall, yet we muſt not lye ſtill and ſleepe in ſinne: but riſe by true Repentance, and ſo runne againe, euen as if our ſpirituall ſtrength were renewed by our fals; knowing this, that in due time wee ſhall reape if wee faint not, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9. And thus by this one Reaſon from a Compariſon, I proue the truth of this my former Doctrine, raiſed from this firſt word of Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Runne:</hi> that all and euery one of thoſe, that doe now profeſſe indeed true Chriſtian Pietie and Religion, they muſt neither ſtand ſtill, nor ſit downe, nor flinch, nor looke back: but muſt hold on ſtill in this Religious Race, vntill they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>in die mortis,</hi> in their day of death, vnto that moſt wiſhed place of eternall life.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this Doctrine, rayſed from this firſt word of Exhortation <hi>Runne:</hi> is of reprehenſion to taxe a number of lazie <hi>Lepid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (I meane, of drowzie Proteſtants and Profeſſors)</hi> now in theſe our dayes and times, who albeit with <hi>Iudas</hi> amongſt the Apoſtles of Chriſt, they doe know as much in Chriſt his Schoole as others doe, and with the diſſembling Phariſes too, in Chriſt his dayes, can profeſſe as much in their golden and glorious words, as the ſoundeſt, and moſt ſanctified Chriſtians that are amongſt vs: yet in all this <hi>interim,</hi> they runne not with perſeuerance in this our true Chriſtian Race. But either they reſemble <hi>Ioſua</hi> his Sunne, which ſtood ſtill by the ſpace of one whole day, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 10.13. or elſe <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his Sun, which went backward ten degrees, <hi>Eſay</hi> 38.8. So doe theſe either ſtand ſtill, or elſe goe backward in goodneſſe: whereas they ſhould reſemble King <hi>Dauids</hi> Sunne, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.5. <hi>Which commeth forth as a Bridegroome out of his Chamber: and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth as a Giant to runne his courſe.</hi> So ſhould theſe (if they were as they ſhould be indeed) ſhake off all ſuch lets &amp; impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments whatſoeuer, as either did clog them that they could not run this Race at all: or elſe did cauſe them to breake off, when as they ſhould continue. To all which drowzie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, (as Gods vnworthy Meſſenger) I muſt bee alſo a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberancer from the Lord, with this my former inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from this firſt word of Exhortation, <hi>Runne:</hi> that all and
<pb facs="tcp:15807:10"/>euery one of thoſe that do now profeſſe indeed true Chriſtian Pietie and Religion: they muſt neither ſtand ſtill, nor ſit downe, nor flinch, nor looke backe, but hold on conſtantly in this Religious Race, vntill they attaine <hi>in die mortis,</hi> vnto that moſt happie and wiſhed place. Whereunto wee haue theſe two mayne Motiues to incite vs (which I beſeech you marke) Firſt, that there is alwayes in true Chriſtianitie, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, a furthermore: as our Apoſtle plainly doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, in the 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Furthermore, we beſeech you Brethren; and exhort you by the Lord Ieſus, that you would abound yet more and more, as yee haue receiued of vs, how yee ought to walke, and to pleaſe God.</hi> And as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> alſo implyeth, in 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Creſcite in gratia; Grow in grace.</hi> And therefore, as <hi>Appelles</hi> Poeſie was this, <hi>Nulla dies ſine linea;</hi> Let no day paſſe without one Line. And as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> Poeſie was, <hi>Chaenici ne inſidias:</hi> Sit not ſtill vpon the Meaſure of Corne. And finall, as the Motto of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth was this: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lterius:</hi> Goe on fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Euen as Chriſt himſelfe ſometimes ſaid to that worthy Gheſt in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.10. <hi>Superius, Sit vp higher:</hi> So according to all theſe particular Directions or Mementoes, (as I may truly tearme them) let vs now runne on ſtill in this Race, without ceaſing. Remembring that heere vpon Earth whiles we are Militant, wee haue not Manſions to reſt in; crying, <hi>Anima requieſce</hi> (as I told you before) but only Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards to worke in. So that in this World wee muſt neuer thinke that in grace we are rich enough: but we muſt bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes poore in ſpirit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.3. we muſt neuer thinke, that we haue either Knowledge, Grace, or Goodneſſe enough; but we muſt alwayes hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſſe: that ſo we may be filled and ſatisfied at the laſt. So then hauing a Talent of Grace, we muſt not put it into a Napkin, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Banke, lighting our Candle; we muſt not ſet it vnder a Buſhell, but on a Candleſticke: Seeking Chriſt, we muſt not ſeeke him in our Beds of reſt, but in our Gardens, and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards of labour, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1. Still caſting off all ſuch clogges and impediments, as may hinder vs in this our Celeſtiall Race.
<pb facs="tcp:15807:11"/>Herein reſembling <hi>Ezechiels</hi> Waters that roſe vp higher and higher, in <hi>Ezec.</hi> 47.4 till we come to our Head, which is the Sonne of God: and that growing Wheate in the Goſpel, which waxed riper and riper, <hi>Marke</hi> 4.28. till we come to that great Harueſt Day, which is in the end of the World.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Motiue to perſwade vs to runne on, with all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible perſeuerance in this our Religious Race, is, for that in our great <hi>Audit</hi> Day, the Day of the Lord: it is not our only Faith of knowing much, which the Deuils haue, <hi>Iames</hi> 2. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. Nor yet our only Faith of aſſenting to much, which our Hypocrites haue, that will then ſuffice, and ſerue our turnes: but only this our true ſauing Faith of knowing, aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and applying of Chriſt with all his benefits vnto our ſelues. The which Faith of ours, if it bee ſound indeed, as it ought to be; it will haue theſe two principall properties, to wit: Firſt, a godly ſorrow, or vnfayned Repentance, for her Gentleman Vſher, as the Faith of the <hi>Ninouites</hi> ſometimes had, <hi>Ionas</hi> 3.10. and ſecondly, thoſe liuely fruits, or effects of the Spirit of God for her Attendants and Companions, mentioned in <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Loue, Ioy, Peace, long ſuffering, &amp;c.</hi> This grace of true ſauing faith, being a moſt glorious Queene. And as Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> ſtileth her, <hi>Ipſa Regina virtutum:</hi> The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Queene of all the Theologicall Vertues: moſt honourably attended euermore as a Queene, with thoſe Celeſtiall Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins the fruits of the Spirit, whereof I ſpake before: as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14, 15. you may runne and reade. And ſo I come from our Apoſtles word of Exhortation, <hi>Runne,</hi> vnto his moſt worthy Direction how, <hi>with patience the Race that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs.</hi> In which Direction, note I pray you theſe two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Points: Firſt, our Apoſtles Metaphoricall word Race: by which Race is heere meant the whole courſe and compaſſe of this our mortall life: and Secondly, that Theologicall Vertue or Grace, wherewith our ſoules muſt bee ſeaſoned, fenced, and guarded, for our more comfortable finiſhing of this our mortall Race, in that one word Patience: <hi>Let vs runne with patience the Race, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:11"/>
            <p> The word Race in the Originall, as I find, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there were three ſeuerall kinds. The firſt of <hi>Italy,</hi> called <hi>Stadium Italicum,</hi> the <hi>Italian</hi> Race: contayning ſixe hundred fiue and twentie feet. The ſecond, <hi>Olympicum:</hi> the Race of <hi>Olympus:</hi> contayning only ſixe hundred feet. And the third and laſt, <hi>Pythicum:</hi> contayning no leſſe then a thouſand feet: which is two hundred paces. Now it is moſt probable, that our Apoſtle in this place, writing to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> alluded to that <hi>Olympian</hi> Race, or Courſe, which of the three is found to bee the ſhorteſt; much like to thoſe Tyes (as they tearme them in <hi>Kent</hi>) which are but ſome thirtie or fortie Rods: and then there ſtands the Goale. And euen ſo likewiſe, this life of ours (as we ſee, and know by daily experience) is but only the laſting and continuance of a few yeeres, moneths, weekes, and dayes at the vttermoſt, and then at laſt comes this death <hi>vpſhot, Mortuus eſt: So this man died, which is the Epitaph of euery man, either firſt, or last.</hi> So that as euery man had a day of Birth: ſo ſhall he haue alſo; &amp; that very ſhortly, a day of Death. For that all our whole courſe and compaſſe here is but as the extent or continuance of a Race, which is but a few feet, or paces of ground, and there is the period or the vttermoſt bound.</p>
            <p>Hence then from this Metaphoricall word Race, there ariſeth this Doctrine for our Learning, that the laſting of this our life vpon Earth, it is exceeding ſhort, and paſſeth verie ſwiftly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> The reaſons for the proofe, &amp; confirmation of this Doctrine, are principally three: whereof the firſt is drawne, from the Scripture <hi>à teſtimonio Spiritus ſancti,</hi> (which is, <hi>Spiritus veritatis</hi> the Spirit of Truth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. &amp; <hi>therefore his</hi> teſtimonie cannot but be true:) in <hi>Iob</hi> 14.1. <hi>Man that is borne of a woman hath but a ſhort time to liue:</hi> And it is moſt truely ſaid, <hi>Quod homo est animal aui breuiſſimi, &amp; ſolicitudinis infinitae: That mans dayes are few, and euill:</hi> (as once old <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid to King <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.9.) <hi>and that his cares and ſorrowes are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite.</hi> So that this our life is not ſhort and ſweete, (as Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures
<pb facs="tcp:15807:12"/>vſe to ſay, though falſly) but very ſhort and ſharpe, as daily triall and (experience prooues vnto vs all moſt plainly) ſome giuing ouer, at their firſt ſetting out in this their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Race, euen in their very Cradles, as did thoſe Infants of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.16. Some others when they haue run ſome three or foure paces in their youth: as did the young man in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.12. Some others about the middeſt of their Race, as did <hi>Lazarus</hi> the Brother of <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Marie,</hi> in <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.14. And ſome when they are almoſt come to the Goale: as old <hi>Simeon</hi> did in <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29. Yea, and moſt men and women are out of breath, before they can reach the ſtayed paces of threeſcore yeeres, and if any doe liue till eightie yeeres, we repute him then exceeding old, as appeares out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. the dayes of the yeeres are threeſcore and tenne: and if by reaſon of ſtrength, they reach to foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeeres, yet is there ſtrength then but labour and ſorrow for it is ſoone cut off, and we flye away. And thus, <hi>à teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio Spiritus Sancti,</hi> I prooue the truth of this my former Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, from this our Apoſtles Metaphoricall word Race, that the laſting of this our life here vpon Earth, it is exceeding ſhort, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Reaſon is drawne, <hi>ab experientia quotidiana,</hi> from daily experience (which is the ſureſt Schoole-miſtris in the World) in that we doe find, perceiue, and ſee by experience: that there are as many ſmall ſculs in our <hi>Golgothaes</hi> (which are our Churches, &amp; Churchyards) as there are great: and that for one Apple which falleth ripe from our Trees, tenne are pulled before they be ripe: and that the Parents do as often naturally mourne for the death of their children, as the children doe for the death of their Parents. Thus being our Aprill and our Iune (as I may terme) in which we flouriſh for a while, but very ſhortly will come our September and Nouember, in which as leaues wee muſt fall to the ground: and what a wonderfull change will this be, that within theſe foureſcore yeeres at the moſt, ſcarce one of all this Congregation ſhall remayne aliue: but another Paſtour and other people, another
<pb facs="tcp:15807:12"/>Preacher, and other hearers ſhall ſupply theſe roomes. The Rauen, and the Phenix, &amp; the Elephant, and the Lion, and the Hart, liue out their hundreds of yeeres: but Man dyeth, when his ſunne is yet but riſen, before his Eye can be ſatisfied with ſeeing, or his Eare with hearing, or his Heart with luſting; Death knocks at the very doore of his heart, and will not ſuffer him to ſtudie for an excuſe, before hee muſt appeare to giue an account of his Stewardſhip, for he can bee no longer ſteward. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.2, 3.</p>
            <p>And euen thus, <hi>Ab experientia quotidiana,</hi> by experience, I proue alſo the truth of this my former Doctrine, raiſed from the word <hi>Race.</hi> That the laſting, and continuance of our life here vpon earth, it is exceeding ſhort, &amp;c. A third reaſon, for further proofe &amp; confirmation of this Doctrine, is drawne <hi>à Comparatis,</hi> from Compariſons, taken out of the pure fountain it ſelfe of Gods bleſſed Booke. In that this preſent life of ours is compared by the Holy Ghoſt in Scripture, ſometimes to a Pilgrimage in which is vncertaintie: as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.9. The dayes of my Pilgrimage are an hundred and thirtie yeeres. Sometimes to Graſſe and Flowers, in which is mutabilitie: as in <hi>Eſay</hi> 40.7. Sometimes to a Smoake, in which is vanitie; as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.3. Sometimes to a houſe of Clay, in which there is miſerie. <hi>Iob.</hi> 4.19. Sometimes to a Weauers ſhittle, in which is volubilitie: as in <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.6. Somtimes to a Shepherds Tent, in which is varietie: as in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 38.12. Sometimes to a Ship vpon the Seas, or to a Poſt vpon the Land, in which is great celeritie: as in <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> 5.9.10. Somtimes to a Race, as in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. And ſo likewiſe heere in this my Text. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to a Dreame, whereof wee haue many in one night: as in <hi>Iob</hi> 20.8. Sometimes to Vanitie, which is nothing in it ſelfe: as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5. And ſometimes to nothing, or a thing of nought, which hath no being in this world: as in the ſelfe ſame <hi>Pſalme</hi> and <hi>Verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which compariſons taken out of the written Word of God, I proue the truth of this my former Doctrine, as by a third reaſon, that the laſting and continuance of our liues
<pb facs="tcp:15807:13"/>here vpon Earth it is exceeding ſhort, &amp; paſſeth very ſwiftly. And no maruel, for that the holy Ghoſt reſembleth Mans pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate: (beſides all thoſe tranſitorie things, which afore I haue mentioned:) ſometimes to a Shadow, which is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the body: as in <hi>Iob</hi> 8.9. And ſometimes to a vapour, which quickly vaniſheth: as in <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.14. Now then, all theſe things of ſo ſhort a continuance, what elſe doe they intimate vnto vs all, but a ſerious conſideration with our ſelues of our moſt ſhort, vnconſtant, and variable eſtate? The chiefeſt of mans glory heere vpon Earth, being reſembled (as before I ſhewed you) but to a Flower: and a Flower (as in Summer wee doe ſee) is a thing of no long continuance: for that the cold nips it, the heate withers it; and laſtly, the ſithe will quickly cut it downe. And euen ſo is our life, in length but as a ſpanne; yea, a very nothing in reſpect of Eternitie. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.4.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this my former Doctrine, raiſed from our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles metaphoricall word <hi>Race,</hi> is of admonition to warne vs all, that ſith this preſent life of ours is ſo exceeding ſhort: (as I haue moſt euidently prooued vnto you, by three moſt pregnant and powerfull reaſons) So that in truth, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of that which followeth, it is but <hi>Punctum temporis, quod hîc viuimus, imò &amp; puncto minus.</hi> But a very moment of time, that heere wee all doe liue. And yet as Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> truely ſayth; <hi>Hoc eſt momentum vnde pendet Aeternitas.</hi> This is that onely moment whereupon dependeth Eternitie. For that if this time bee well ſpent, then of our liuing in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Felicitie: but if this bee miſpent, then of our liuing in eternall Miſerie. That therefore we bee now mindfull and carefull euery day, for to ſpend it well, and to make good vſe indeed, of this ſo ſhort a moment of our time, in running of this our Chriſtian race aright: by liuing Religiouſly towards God; Soberly towards our ſelues, and juſtly and ſquarely one towards another: taking eſpeciall heed of all carnall ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Conſidering, that which way ſoeuer we caſt our eyes, we haue great cauſe of vigilancy, but none at all of ſecuritie. For
<pb facs="tcp:15807:13"/>if wee looke vpward, let vs thinke vpon God, whom by our ſinnes wee haue moſt juſtly diſpleaſed: if downeward, vpon Hell, which wee haue all of vs deſerued: if backward, vpon our Sinnes, which we haue formerly committed: if forward, vpon our Death and Iudgement, which cannot bee auoyded if inward, vpon our owne Conſciences, which wee haue defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: if outward, vpon this wicked World, which to too much wee haue loued. Let vs all now conſider whence firſt we came, and bluſh, where wee are: and ſigh, whither we are going, and tremble: and laſtly, how ſhort this our life is, and prepare. And now to this end, that wee may all of vs the more directly runne in this our Religious race as we ought to doe; without ſtanding, ſitting, fainting, flinching, or loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king backe. Two ſpeciall rules muſt bee well learned of vs; to wit; Firſt, a due Preparation before: and ſecondly, a right Diſpoſition of our ſelues, in running of this Religious race a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right as wee ought to doe.</p>
            <p>For the firſt rule. Our due Preparation before, doth chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſt in theſe two principall points. Firſt, in dyeting of our ſelues afore-hand, from forbearing the pleaſing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightſome practice of all our old and wonted ſinnes: euen as earthly Runners in a corporall Race, doe keepe themſelues to a bodily dyet before their Running day. Secondly, in the ſtripping and ſhifting cleane of our ſelues, from the filthy rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ragges of our owne ſuppoſed righteouſneſſe, (which is all but like to a menſtruous Cloath, as in <hi>Eſay</hi> 64.6.) euen as earthly Runners ſtrip and ſhift themſelues of their daily wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Cloathes, before they doe ſet forth.</p>
            <p>And as for our ſecond and laſt former rule, <hi>viz.</hi> Our right Diſpoſition in running, it conſiſteth in theſe three principall things. Firſt, in our beginning well, for that (as the Poet ſayd of old.) <hi>Dimidium facti, qui bene caepit habet.</hi> Hee that hath made a good beginning, hath therein halfe finiſhed this his Running, being guided herein by the Word of God and Prayer. Secondly, in going on well, not in the wry way of <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> nor in the by-way of <hi>Papiſme,</hi> but only in that old
<pb facs="tcp:15807:14"/>way, which is the good and right way of <hi>Chriſtianiſme.</hi> That is, <hi>In ſemita Dei ſtatutorum,</hi> onely in the path of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. Thirdly and laſt of all, In ending well. <hi>For that wee vſually ſay, and not vntruely, if the End bee well, then all is well.</hi> As our Sauiour himſelfe doth teach vs, in <hi>Math.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Qui perſeuerat vſque ad finem ſaluus erit.</hi> He alone which continueth vnto the end ſhall bee ſaued. For that <hi>ſola perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerantia Coronatur,</hi> onely our perſeuerance in this Race, will enrich vs with the Crowne. And in deed and truth, (as a godly Father ſayth) <hi>Incaſſum in hoc ſtadio curritur, ſi ante vitae terminum deſeratur.</hi> As good not at all to begin this Race, as to giue off againe before our dying day. The which Truth, is taught vs by Chriſt himſelfe, in <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.62. Whoſoeuer ſhall put his hand to the Lords Plough, and then looke backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, is vnfit for the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore now labour, not onely to enter, but once being entred, carefully and conſtantly to hold on in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious race, to the vttermoſt end, and <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of our liues, that ſo in death we may take hold by Faith, of that our ineſtimable prize which is Eternall life. Cloſing vp this our Race, when wee ſhall come to the goale, with that ſweet and comfortable concluſion of our bleſſed Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7.8. I haue fought the good fight of Faith; I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the Faith: from henceforth there is layed vp for me the Crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord that righteous Iudge ſhall giue vnto me, and not to me onely, but to all them that loue his appearing. And ſo I come from this Metaphoricall word <hi>Race,</hi> to that Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call grace or vertue it ſelfe: wherewith our hearts muſt bee fortified, fenced, &amp; guarded, for our more comfortable running and finiſhing of this our Religious race, moſt liuely layed downe in that one word, <hi>Patience. Let vs runne with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Patience,</hi> is deſcribed for to bee a moſt excellent gift, or grace of God, whereby all Gods militant Saints heere vpon Earth, are enabled to beare quietly, peaceably, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly, all Croſſes and Contumelies, whatſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe the Lord for to lay vpon them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:14"/>
            <p> And hence there ariſeth this Doctrine, or leſſon for our learning, that true Patience indeed in vndergoing of croſſes, is a moſt needfull and gainefull part of euery true Chriſtians ſpirituall Armour, for the fitting, fencing, and furniſhing of him, to runne this Religious race aright. The firſt reaſon, for proofe of this Doctrine, is drawne <hi>à preſenti conditione Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> from the preſent troubleſome eſtate of all Gods militant Saints. For that euen a whole world of troubles, tryals and croſſes, muſt be vndergone of them in this preſent world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can come to the goales end, &amp; enjoy euerlaſting reſt and happineſſe in Heauen: as in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.33. in <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.27. in <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22. and in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6.7. (being the very Chapter it ſelfe, from whence this my Text is taken) you may runne and reade. To all which places of Scripture; for breuitie, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre you. For that all theſe particuler places doe ſhew how rough, and full of Thornes our way to Heauen is, in this our Spirituall race. Exeperience whereof, the Hiſtories of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges doe moſt apparantly proue vnto vs.</p>
            <p>As namely of <hi>Abel, Noah, Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob,</hi> and his poſteritie in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, in <hi>Canaan,</hi> vnder Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, vnder Kings, and in their Captiuities. <hi>Quis Sanctorum,</hi> ſayth Saint <hi>Hierom, ſine certamine Coronatus est.</hi> Which of all the Saints was euer Crowned without croſſing, without fighting, without ſuffering? Let vs but ſeriouſly conſider with our ſelues, the liues of Chriſt, and of his Prophets and Apoſtles: and the eſtate of Gods Church in the Apoſtles time, and after their time, and euer ſince, to theſe our dayes and times, and wee ſhall quickly find, that it were an infinite worke to reckon vp onely all the perſecutions, troubles, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and ſundry kinde of Croſſes, which Gods owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his delicate ones, from time to time haue endured in this preſent life. And no maruell; for that as impoſſible as it is for Sheepe to liue quiet amongſt Wolues without hurt: or for <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke to bee without floating vpon the Waters: or for Chriſt his Ship to bee without danger of ſinking vpon the Seas: or finally, for a Lilly to bee without pricking, growing
<pb facs="tcp:15807:15"/>among Thornes: ſo impoſſible is it for Gods militant Church to bee without troubles and tryals, and perſecutions in this preſent world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But heere now me thinkes, I heare ſome ſay vnto me, that all Ages and Times, haue not beene times of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions vnto the Church of God. For that the Church of God in Kings <hi>Salomons</hi> dayes, and ſo likewiſe vnder the raigne of many other good Kings and Princes, had very great peace and quiet. And in <hi>Act.</hi> 9.31. wee doe finde that in the Apoſtles dayes, which were troubleſome times, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches had reſt. And ſo likewiſe in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt worthy Chriſtian Emperours. And euen ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (bleſſed bee God) heere in this our Iland, vnder the peaceable raigne of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and our moſt Gracious King IAMES, whom the Lord of his goodneſſe long continue amongſt vs, if it bee his bleſſed will, euen as the dayes of Heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though Gods militant Church, and the members thereof, bee freed for a ſeaſon from all outward publike perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of the cruell Magiſtrates, or from open inuaſions of their forraigne Foes, yet neuer fully free from all manner of troubles. For that as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.19. Many are the troubles of the Righteous; yea, euen in the moſt halcion and peaceable dayes and times that euer were. And no maruell; For behold in the boſome of Gods Church heere vpon Earth, there haue alwayes beene, ſtill are, and euer will bee, ſome <hi>Iſmaels</hi> as well as <hi>Iſaacs;</hi> ſome <hi>Eſaus</hi> as well as <hi>Iacobs;</hi> ſome borne car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally after the fleſh onely, as well as ſome new borne againe after the Spirit of God. Which being ſo indeed, there will therefore euermore bee perſecution of Gods Church vpon Earth; if not with Fire, Sword, Baniſhment, Impriſonment, and with ſuch like outward tortures and torments; yet with Ignominies, reproches, taunts, and diſgraces, &amp; with ſuch like <hi>Iſmaeliticall</hi> perſecutions, which wil go as neere to the harts, and pierce thorow the very ſoules of Gods Saints, as deepely as the other. And thus in the moſt quiet times of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:15807:15"/>Church militant; hee that refraineth from euill, maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a prey. Many and manifold iniuries, both in body, goods and name, doe the true Saints of God receiue from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked neighbours, being often diſgraced and oppreſſed of the greater ſort, and many times reuiled and wronged of the meaner ſort. And if in this life they ſhould haue peace abroad, yet at home, euen in their owne priuate Families, ſhall they finde tryals and troubles enough, ariſing ordinarily from their Parents, Husbands, Wiues, Children, Seruants, Friends, Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and the like. Hence then from our preſent condition heere in this life, wherein wee all are ſubject to ſo many ſtormes, and doe daily meete with ſuch an ocean of troubles, I proue the truth of this my former Doctrine, that of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wee muſt ſtriue to bee fenced, and fitted with <hi>Patience,</hi> for the finiſhing of this Religious race.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon, for proofe and confirmation of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is drawne <hi>Ab vtili, ſeu commodo Patientiae.</hi> From the vnſpeakeable gaine and profit, of this moſt excellent pearle of Patience. <hi>For that euen as the lidde is made by God to open and to ſhut againe, to ſaue the Eye from hurts and harmes: ſo Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſet to keepe our Soules, and to ſaue whole our Hearts, and to cheere vp our Bodies againe.</hi> And therefore if wee obſerue it, when we can goe by offences, and put vp wrongs, and ſuffer troubles quietly, wee ſhall finde a kinde of peace and joy in our hearts, as though we had gotten ſome victorie; and the more that our Patience doth increaſe, the more our Paines will ſtill decreaſe. For euen as a light burthen borne at our armes length, will weigh much heauier then a burthen of treble weight layed vpon our ſhoulders, which are made to beare. So if wee take impatience to beare all our Croſſes, which is not fit to beare them! O then we will immediately murmur, and grudge, and ſhrinke, and ſtart, and let our bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then fall: but if once wee put Patience for to beare them, which is made to beare them all indeed. O then, euen as thoſe heartie Spies which came from <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſayd, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ouercome them. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 2. So will Patience ſay vnto vs
<pb facs="tcp:15807:16"/>amidſt all our croſſes it is nothing to be belyed, nothing to be enuied, nothing to bee back-byted, nothing to bee ſlandered, nothing to be impriſoned, &amp;c. as though all theſe things did come vpon vs, not to make vs conquered, but rather by our patience to make vs Conquerours. And thus all is (as we ſee) in the manner of bearing of the Croſſe, which makes perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution ſeeme joyfull to ſome, and irkſome to others: which makes pouertie welcome to ſome, and bitter to others: which makes ſome ſing in their ſickneſſe, as if they were whole, and others to raue, and whine, and curſe, as they were not ſicke but franticke. And therefore Chriſt his yoke is ſtiled eaſie, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. becauſe it is made eaſie to ſome that haue pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to beare it. As Chriſt by his infinite patience did ſuffer infinite paines for our infinite ſinnes: ſo ſhall we beare all our croſſes that come vpon vs in this our Chriſtian Race, if wee haue this one Preſeruatiue of patience about vs. For what elſe hath the poore man to beare his pouertie? or the ſicke man his paines? or the bond-man his bondage? or the bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed man his exile? but only to lay all vpon the ſhoulders of patience, and to ſay, with <hi>Ieremy</hi> in all his trials, <hi>This is my ſorrow, and I will beare it, Ier.</hi> 10. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. In <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.25. we do reade, <hi>That the Tree which</hi> Moſes <hi>caſt into the Spring did ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the bitterneſſe of the waters:</hi> So this Tree of patience, being caſt into our troubles, will ſeaſon the bitterneſſe of all our croſſes, and will aſſiſt vs to ouercome all our trials and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: like that Armour-bearer, which holpe good <hi>Ionathan</hi> to vanquiſh all his enemies, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>And no maruell, for that this moſt excellent grace of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, hath a deuice (as one wittily writeth) to draw ſuch a skinne ouer all our ſoares and ſorrowes, as to make our pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſeeme Riches, our Reproaches ſeeme Honours, our Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage ſeeme Libertie, our Labours ſeeme Reſt, our Sorrowes ſeemes Ioyes, our Paines ſeeme Pleaſures, our Sickneſſe ſeeme Health, and all things that hurt vs to rejoyce vs: vntill wee doe ſay with holy <hi>Dauid; Behold, thy Iudgements are good, Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>Ver.</hi> 39. And for want of which moſt worthy grace,
<pb facs="tcp:15807:16"/>many thinke themſelues in Hell, amidſt there earthly woes; and ſay, that no mans paines are like their paines, no mans wants like their wants, no mans foes like their foes, no mans wrongs like their wrongs, when as they can ſcarcely tell, where their paine doth hold them. And therefore, euen thoſe which cannot ſuffer that they might haue reſt, yet ſing that old and patient Prouerbe: <hi>Of ſufferance comes reſt.</hi> So many and manifold, being the effects and fruits of this Theologicall grace of Patience: that as a godly Father ſaith; Firſt, <hi>In pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia (vt in arca) anima noſtra cuſtoditur:</hi> By patience our Soules are kept in ſafetie, as earthly Treaſure is in ſome Iron Chiſt: which our Sauiour himſelfe doth teach vs; ſaying, in <hi>Luke</hi> 21.19. <hi>In patientia poſſidete animas veſtras:</hi> By your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience poſſeſſe your ſoules. Secondly, <hi>In patientia vita guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> By Patience our whole life is led, ordered and guided: for which cauſe the Holy Ghoſt doth plainly tell vs, <hi>That hee which is patient, is of great vnderstanding, Prou.</hi> 14.29. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Per patientiam qualis homo ſit probatur: By patience a man is proued what a one he is:</hi> as in <hi>Prou.</hi> 27. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 21. As the fining Pot for Siluer, and the Fornace for Gold, ſo is a patient man to his praiſe. Fourth, <hi>Per patientiam victoria acquiritur:</hi> By patience we become Conquerors ouer all our troubles. So that as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>Qui verè patiens eſt, à toto mundo vinci non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit.</hi> Hee which is truly patient, no croſſes can ouercome him, but he ouercomes them all: according to that old ſaying, <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit qui patitur:</hi> Hee which is patient ſhall ouercome. For which cauſe in <hi>Reuel.</hi> 13.10. and in <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.12. When the Holy there ſpeakes of the victory of the Saints; hee ſaith, here is the patience of the Saints. Noting that by their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience they ouercame all their troubles: and therefore in <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.5. We are all of vs exhorted, let patience haue her perfect worke. For that <hi>Nobile genus vincendi eſt patientia.</hi> Patience is a moſt noble kind of conquering. Now then your patience may haue her perfect Worke. Firſt, it muſt bee ſound and heartie, and not fayned and counterfeit. For that as ſoundnes and integritie is a kind of perfection in all Chriſtian graces,
<pb facs="tcp:15807:17"/>ſo alſo in patience. Secondly, It muſt extend to all our croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, both heauie and light; inward and outward, at home and abroad, whither from the Deuill, or from any of his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: or elſe from God himſelfe, as his owne immediate hand. And laſtly, of what kind, qualitie and quantitie ſoeuer they be, as the Holy Ghoſt implyeth, ſaying, in 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4. We approoue our ſelues in much patience. Thirdly and laſt of all for the continuance it muſt endure vnto the end of our Race. So as wee muſt both patiently beare the preſent, and ſo likewiſe prepare and fit our ſelues for future croſſes. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring ſtill, <hi>that hee which hath patience to the end ſhall bee ſaued, Mat.</hi> 10.22. Thus the patience of <hi>Iob</hi> had her perfect worke in all theſe three reſpects. For firſt it was ſound, and of a large extent, or elſe he could not haue ſo ſtood againſt all his friends, and amidſt all his trials, ſo vprightly as hee did: and finally, it continued vnto the end, for hee was ouercome by none of them, but hee by patience ouercame them all: as we may runne and reade in <hi>Iob</hi> 13.15. and 42.7. whoſe Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by Saint <hi>Iames</hi> is propoſed for our practice, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.11. and that not vnfitly. Firſt, in regard of the greatneſſe of our trials and troubles in this preſent life: becauſe they are not Scar-crowes, or troubles in ſhew which we ſuffer, but ſuch as pierce both our bodies and our ſoules. Secondly, becauſe that the number of our trials is to vs vncertayne, (our cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities as waues falling one vpon another) and thirdly and laſtly, becauſe that their continuance is alſo vncertayne, as is the continuance of our life.</p>
            <p>This whole life (as I haue taught you) being but a Race, ſo that ſo long as wee are Runners in this Race: ſo long wee muſt looke for many ſtormes and temptations. Now then for vs to faint before we haue ended our Race, is worſe then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue endured any whit at all. In that not only the glorie of all our former patience is vtterly loſt, but alſo turned into ſhame. Firſt, Ignominie, and our God prouoked vtterly to forſake vs, and to haue no pleaſure in vs, as in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. and therefore euermore amidſt all our croſſes, wee muſt ſtill
<pb facs="tcp:15807:17"/>remember this ſhort cloſe, <hi>Si vis vincere, diſce pati.</hi> Learne to be patient if thou looke to conquer. And thus, <hi>ab vtili patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> from the gaine of this moſt excellent grace of patience, I proue alſo the truth of this my former Doctrine; That true patience indeed amidſt all our croſſes, is a moſt needfull and gainfull grace, for the fitting, fencing, and furniſhing of our ſoule to runne this Religious Race.</p>
            <p>The Vſe is of admonition to warne vs all, to labour for this Celeſtiall Herbe of grace &amp; of patience, that ſo we may haue it ſtill ſprouting and ſpringing in the ſpirituall Gardens of our hearts and liues. Knowing well, that God hath giuen ſuch a wonderfull power to this Medicinable Herbe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect patience, that it ſhall bee an acceptable Medicament to a generall ſalue for all perſons, and for all Diſeaſes. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>Reuel.</hi> 13.10. wee doe reade that when Gods Angell had recorded all the troubles, which ſhould come into the World in the latter dayes, at laſt hee cloſeth and concludeth thus. <hi>Heere is the Patience and Faith of the Saints.</hi> As if pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſhould beare and ouercome them all. And for this very cauſe throughout the whole bodie of the Bible: ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Sentences of Scripture are written and placed, as ſo many Preachers to exhort vs vnto patience, as in <hi>Luke</hi> 19.21 <hi>By your patience poſſeſſe your ſoule,</hi> and in <hi>Prou.</hi> 14.29. <hi>A mans wiſdome is knowne by his patience.</hi> And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36. <hi>Wee haue need of patience, that after that we haue done the will of God, we might receiue the promiſe.</hi> And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Patience breedes experience, experience hope; and hope maketh not aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe, in <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.7, 8. <hi>Bee patient Brethren to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> And beſides all theſe powerfull Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations vnto patience, the Prophets, Euangeliſts, and Apoſtles, haue ſet forth a number of Examples before our eyes, like Beacons vpon the tops of Hils, of ſuch great Cures as haue beene healed by patience. So that what our Apoſtle ſaith of Faith, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. from the fourth <hi>Verſe</hi> to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth, the very ſame may I ſay of this grace of patience. By patience holy <hi>Iob</hi> did beare all the trials that the Deuill could
<pb facs="tcp:15807:18"/>poſſibly heape vpon him, <hi>Iob</hi> 1. By patience <hi>Iacob</hi> put a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of wrongs at the hands of <hi>Laban,</hi> his Father-in-law, and neuer once complained in one and twenty yeeres, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.7. By patience good <hi>Ioſeph</hi> forgaue all his Brethren, when hee might haue put them all to death: and gaue them food for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.15, 17. By patience <hi>Dauid</hi> ouercame all his croſſes: though hee had King <hi>Saul</hi> that mighty one againſt him; the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> againſt him, the <hi>Ammonites</hi> againſt him, the <hi>Edomites</hi> againſt him, the <hi>Moabites</hi> againſt him; and laſtly, <hi>Abſalom</hi> his owne bowels againſt him. For whom hee cryed, ſaying, would God I had dyed for thee, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33. Yet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtill comforted himſelfe in the Lord his God, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. euen as if this moſt precious Pearle of patience, were the only ſpiritual ſtone vpon which he leaned and reſted his head. Laſtly, by patience our Lord &amp; Maſter Chriſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Baniſhment, Reproaches, Taunts, and Scourges, vntill laſt of all hee went to his death, like a Lambe to the ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But here now (me thinkes) I heare ſome ſay vnto me; how may wee get and obtayne this ſpirituall Armour of proofe, this Pearle of Patience: which is ſo needfull and gainfull a graine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, by labouring to bee furniſhed with Faith to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God. For that whoſoeuer doth know perfectly, and is ſure in his heart by Faith, that God who is the Lord of all haps and miſhaps, of proſperitie and aduerſitie, of health and ſickneſſe. Life and death is pacified, and fully reconciled with him by Ieſus Chriſt, ſo that hee cannot poſſibly bee depriued of eternall ſaluation; to ſuch a true beleeuing Chriſtian man, there can be no croſſe ſo ſharpe, bitter, and grieuous vnto him, as can poſſibly bring him out of patience. But by faith hee ſhall ſtill obtayne and keepe this precious Pearle and Iewel of patience, as in <hi>Iames</hi> 1.3. <hi>The tryall of your Faith worketh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience;</hi> the which faith, though in this life it bee little and weake in the beſt, and deareſt of Gods children heere: and in time of tryall and affliction beginne to draw backe, and proue like to a brand that hath but little fire in it: yet ought wee
<pb facs="tcp:15807:18"/>not to deſpayre, but to remember that the Lord Ieſus will not quench, but increaſe it: ſo as wee doe but pray with the bleſſed Apoſtles, <hi>O Lord increaſe our Faith, Luke</hi> 17.5. And with the Father of him that was poſſeſſed, <hi>Lord, wee beleeue, helpe our vnbeliefe, Marke</hi> 9.24. Secondly, ſound hope, which is the Daughter of a true faith, maketh men to bee patient, when as they hope &amp; truſt for honor, &amp; reward after all their ſuffrings, as in <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.25. If we hope for that we ſee not, then do we with patience wait for it. Thirdly, faithfull and feruent Prayer maketh men to be patient: for that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. hee hath promiſed, doe but aske and haue, &amp;c. And if experience prooues this much vnto vs, that when once we haue but ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our needs and griefs to our friends, we do afterward feele a certain eaſe in our ſelues, ſo that our former paine and griefe is ſomewhat remedied and taken away; O then much more comfort, and eaſe ſhall we find from God, to the quieting and ſetling of our mindes, by the opening of our griefes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints vnto God in humble Prayer. Fourthly, diligent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſearching, and ſeeking into Gods moſt holy, &amp; bleſſed Word, helpeth much vnto patience, wherein he doth ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes his moſt ſweete and louing promiſes, as in <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.33. <hi>Theſe things haue I ſpoken vnto you, that in me you might haue peace, in the World you muſt ſuffer tribulation. But bee of good comfort, I haue, &amp;c.</hi> In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Call vpon mee in the time of trouble, I will heare thee, and thou ſhalt prayſe mee:</hi> with ſuch like gracious promiſes, which we ought daily to ſeek, &amp; ſearch in his Sacred word, neuer ceaſing to laude &amp; prayſe his holy Name, in that in theſe our dayes and times he hath made vs rich partakers of theſe moſt ſweete and infallible comforts for our ſoules, in his Word and Goſpel: which Word wee ought all to beleeue, receiue and obey, euen as though wee heard the immediate voyce of God himſelfe from Heauen, ſpeaking all ſuch things as we heare out of the ſame. Fiftly, and laſtly, a true loue waxing and ſprinkling out of faith, will worke in vs this worthy grace of patience; in <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.20. It is ſaid that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſerued ſeuen yeeres for <hi>Rachel,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:15807:19"/>they ſeemed vnto him but a few dayes, becauſe hee loued her: So likewiſe, whoſoeuer truly loueth God, he will beare and take moſt patiently whatſoeuer tryals and troubles God ſhall lay vpon him; and whatſoeuer here he ſuffereth for Chriſt his ſake, it ſhall be eaſie vnto him. So that ſtill hee will be readie to runne after him, through all manner of wayes bee they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo rough, vntill ſuch time as hee may come at laſt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and eternall reſt in him.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come from our Apoſtles Direction, <hi>with patience the race that is ſet before vs.</hi> The laſt part of this my Text, which is his Demonſtration: drawne <hi>ab exemplo Ieſu Chriſti,</hi> in theſe laſt words: <hi>Looking to Ieſus.</hi> Not looking to the World, <hi>Quia mundus deficiet:</hi> becauſe that the World will forſake and leaue vs, and we muſt leaue the World, wee cannot tell how ſoone, as in <hi>Prou.</hi> 27.1. <hi>Boast not thy ſelfe of to morrow, for thou canſt not tell what a day may bring forth.</hi> Nor yet looking to our owne rebellious fleſh; <hi>Quia care irficiet:</hi> our fleſh will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and poyſon our ſoules; ſo that if wee liue after the fleſh, we ſhall dye, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. Nor yet looking to Satan, <hi>Quia Diabolus interficiet;</hi> The Deuill will deſtroy vs, walking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout continually like a roaring Lion, ſeeking whom hee may deuoure, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. but, as it is here in this my Text; <hi>Looking to Ieſus: Quia reficiet:</hi> for that he will eaſe vs, hee will refreſh vs, hee will direct vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> And hence there ariſeth this Doctrine for our Learning, that in running of this our Religious Race: the life of our Lord and Maſter Ieſus, muſt be our Spirituall Card and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe; our only Line, and Ieuell for to guide vs by.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon for proofe and confirmation of this my laſt Leſſon, for breuitie ſhall be but one; drawne <hi>Ab ipſiſſima vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Ieſu Chriſti:</hi> becauſe that in his life, hee both was, and is the Lord of all Vertues: and therefore he ſayth thus to all his Diſciples: <hi>Diſcite à me:</hi> Learne of me, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quimini me:</hi> follow me.</p>
            <p>For where in all the whole World can wee ſooner fiud true Humilitie, perfect Charitie, Sobrietie, Patience, Obedience,
<pb facs="tcp:15807:19"/>and Prayer without Example, with all other co-adjoyned, and allied Vertues, then in Chriſt his life? of whoſe life Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth thus. Thou haſt O Chriſtian Soule (ſaith he) in the life of Chriſt alone, a moſt Celeſtiall Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine to helpe all thy defects. For what Pride is there in thee, that his Humility cannot abate? What Wrath and Anger, that his Gentleneſſe cannot lenifie? What Couetouſneſſe, that his Pouertie cannot ſalue? What benummedneſſe of thine heart, that his Loue cannot inflame? And as Chriſt his life is a moſt Celeſtiall Medicine for all the Defects and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of our Soules; ſo is it a moſt abſolute Rule or Square, of moſt perfect Diſcipline for our liues. For where I pray you, can we behold ſuch a Preſident without paralell of Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Charitie, Patience, Chaſtitie, Obedience, Sobrietie, and generally, and in a word of all Vertues, then in the life of Chriſt? Where is there true Wiſdome more to be found, then in the Doctrine of Chriſt? Where true Fortitude, then in the Death and Paſſion of Chriſt? Where true Clemencie, then in the Mercy of Chriſt? Where true Humilitie then in the obedience of Chriſt? Where true Charitie, then in the forgiueneſſe of Chriſt? What, I pray doe wee learne by his baſe lying in the Manger at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and by his poore bringing vp in a meane Hoſtage at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> but an vtter contempt of this wicked World? What learne wee by his Exile into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and by his Birth in the dayes of cruell <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> but patient ſuffering hereof Perſecution? What learne we by his Faſting in the Wilderneſſe, the Auſteritie of his life; and conflict with Satan? But how to bee able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all Temptations? What learne we by all his Contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and Reproaches offered vnto him by his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen the <hi>Iewes:</hi> calling him a Blaſphemer, a Seducer of the people; and a friend of <hi>Publicans</hi> and Sinners: but ſtill to poſſeſſe our ſoules by Patience? What laſtly learne wee, by his moſt heartie Prayers to God his heauenly Father for his moſt bloudie Perſecutours (yea, euen in the bitter pangs of death vpon the Croſſe) but a Leſſon of Charitie. If we ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:15807:20"/>of this World, and of worldy things: Who euer reſpected them leſſe then he? But if we ſpeake of heauen and of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, who euer tended and tendred them more then he? If we ſpeake of Almes, where euer was there ſuch an Almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer heard off as he, who freely gaue his own bodie and bloud to refreſh the hungry? If we ſpeake of Bountifulneſſe, where euer was there ſo bountifull a giuer as hee, who gaue Paradiſe it ſelfe to a ſinfull Suter, only vpon the very firſt motion made vnto him? Finally, what Grace I pray you can any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian mans heart deſire, which is not to bee found with much ſpirituall delight in the life of Chriſt? Or what any one Vertue can wee wiſh, but that in him we may euidently ſee, a moſt liuely <hi>Idea,</hi> or Image of the ſame? Thus hath our Lord and Maſter Chriſt done his part, and conformed himſelf vnto vs: &amp; what now remayneth on our parts, but that we ſtriue to conforme our ſelues to him, <hi>Who is the Way, the Truth, and the Life, Iohn</hi> 14.6. The Way without erring, the Truth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out failing: the Life without fading: the Way by Example, the Truth by Promiſe, Life by Reward. In the way of Life, (which is, <hi>The Chriſtians Race</hi>) whom may wee more ſafely follow, then the way it ſelfe? They cannot goe amiſſe, whoſe Guide is the Way: they cannot erre, whoſe Director is the Truth: they cannot periſh, whoſe Preſeruer is the Life.</p>
            <p>And therefore euermore in this our Religious Race, wee muſt looke to Ieſus; but not to his Miracles to be Imitators of them: For that, <hi>Quae ſupra nos nihil ad nos:</hi> theſe all are far aboue our abilities: being euident Teſtimonies of his Deitie: but only to his Vertues, to be followers of them. For behold, he neuer commanded vs; ſaying, Learne of me to faſt fortie dayes and fortie nights: to walk vpon the waters, to caſt out Deuils, to rayſe the Dead, &amp;c. But learne of me to be meeke, and lowly, to loue your enemies, to ſuffer affliction, &amp;c. The olde Eagle for to learne her young Ones to flye, doth often flutter and houer ouer them: So our Maſter Chriſt to teach vs how to liue, both by his Precepts, and Examples of Pietie, doth daily flutter and houer ouer vs in this preſent life. In
<pb facs="tcp:15807:20"/>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.15. When our Sauiour would perſwade his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and followers vnto Humilitie and Loue; hee ſayth, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di vobis exemplum, &amp;c.</hi> I haue giuen you an Example, that you ſhould doe as I haue done to you. And in the 1. of <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. When as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> would perſwade vs to patient Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, hee ſayth; CHRIST alſo ſuffered for vs, leauing vs an Example that wee ſhould follow his ſteps. And in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. When Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would incite the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for to follow him, hee tels them plainely that his meaning was, that indeed they ſhould follow CHRIST; ſaying, Be yee followers of mee euen as I follow Chriſt. And in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.32. When as the ſame Apoſtle would perſwade the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> to forgiue one another, hee ſayth; Forgiue yee one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as CHRIST forgaue you. And finally in the 1. of <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.6. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> layes downe this point of Doctrine moſt plainly vnto vs, ſaying; Hee that abideth in him, ought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to walke, euen as hee walked, ſtill <hi>looking to Ieſus;</hi> euen as Saylers doe to their Sterne, and as Runners to their Goale. And thus <hi>Ab ipſiſſima vita Christi,</hi> I prooue the truth of this my former Doctrine, that in Running of this our Religious Race, the holy Life of our Lord and Maſter CHRIST, muſt bee our Coeleſtiall Card and Compaſſe, it muſt bee our onely leuell and our line for to guide vs by.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Vſe is of reprehenſion to checke, and ſharpely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the Spiritually blinde, (I meane the ignorant <hi>Papiſts</hi>) of theſe our dayes and times, who in ſtead of their looking vnto the life of IESVS, and to his Precepts, Practice, and Preſidents, as this our Text doth teach them: looke either to the Pardons, and Indulgences of the holy Father the Pope, or elſe to the Diabolicall and damnable rules, of his Ieſuites (thoſe <hi>Iebuſites</hi>) his Seminary Prieſts: preferring moſt groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the rules of his <hi>Franciſcan</hi> and <hi>Benedictine</hi> Friars, &amp;c. before this one onely moſt excellent rule of the life of <hi>Christ:</hi> or elſe they looke altogether to their own Merits &amp; Works, which will vtterly deceiue them at the laſt, if they renounce not all theſe, <hi>and looke onely vnto Ieſus.</hi> For that of the firſt they are
<pb facs="tcp:15807:21"/>taught by IESVS himſelfe; That they are but blind leaders of the blinde, and if the blind leade the blind they both ſhall fall into the Ditch. <hi>Math.</hi> 15.14. And of their ſecond, which are our owne good workes, wee are taught out of his moſt bleſſed Booke: that <hi>Opera noſtra per ſe, nihil mereri poſſint:</hi> the beſt good Workes that heere wee can doe, deſerue rather damnation then ſaluation in themſelues. Firſt, <hi>Quia non ſunt noſtra, ſed Dei opera in nobis.</hi> Not our owne, but the workes of God in vs, as in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Quid habes quod non accepiſts.</hi> If a good Thought, this is Grace infuſed; if a good Word, this is Grace effuſed; if a good Worke, this is Grace diffuſed. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Quia non ſunt gratuita, ſed debita.</hi> Not free at our owne pleaſures to doe, or elſe to leaue vndone, but which we muſt doe by bounden dutie: as in <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.9, 10. <hi>Verſes.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Quia non ſnnt perfecta, ſed imperfecta.</hi> Not perfect, but full of infinite imperfections: as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. We haue heere but onely the firſt fruits of the Spirit, and an earneſt penie onely, and no more. Fourthly and laſtly, <hi>Quia non ſunt pura, ſed multis peccatis ſunt permixta.</hi> They are not pure, but like po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Cloutes. <hi>Eſay</hi> 64.6. <hi>Verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that Eternall life, which we looke for in the end of our liues, is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Debitum,</hi> a Debt, or Dutie which our God doth owe vs: but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Donum,</hi> the free Gift of our God: as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. Eternall life is the gift of God, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. So that notwithſtanding all our owne good Workes, yet wee muſt <hi>looke to Ieſus;</hi> And onely to his Actiue and Paſſiue workes, which hee alone hath both done, and endured for vs. Concluding with that Learned Father Saint <hi>Austen. Quod meritis quidem noſtris damnamur, ſed non ſaluamur, niſi tantum meritis Ieſu Christi.</hi> By our owne good Workes wee are damned, but cannot bee ſaued at all, ſaue onely by the Merits and good Workes of our Lord and onely Sauiour IESVS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But heere now me thinkes I heare ſome ignorant Papiſts ſay: If wee are not ſaued at all by our owne good Workes? Why then is life Eternall ſtiled <hi>Merces,</hi> our wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb facs="tcp:15807:21"/>or our hyre. <hi>Math.</hi> 20.10. Which is euermore payed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men for their Workes ſake?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, the wages which is ſo payed amongſt men, is <hi>merces Legalis,</hi> a Legall wages or hyre: but this of Eternall life from GOD, is <hi>merces Euangelica,</hi> an Euangelicall hyre: not <hi>merces debita,</hi> a deſerued hyre, as the Legall is: but onely <hi>indebita,</hi> altogether vndeſerued: and yet moſt truely an hyre, for theſe two cauſes. Firſt, <hi>Ob conſecutionem,</hi> becauſe it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after our good Workes, although freely giuen vs of Gods fauour in Chriſt. And ſecondly, <hi>Ob promiſſionem,</hi> becauſe that God himſelfe hath Promiſed it vnto all his Saints.</p>
            <p>And thus, as moſt excellently ſayth Saint <hi>Auſten. Non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendo, ſed permittendo Deus ſe fecit debitorem.</hi> Our good God is now become a debtor vnto vs, not of any dutie that hee owes vs at all, but onely out of his moſt Gracious promiſe, which hee hath openly made vnto all his Elect. Be aſhamed therefore! O yee ignorant Papiſts, of all your beſt good workes that you can doe, and notwithſtanding all theſe, yet <hi>Oculo fidei,</hi> with the Spirituall eye of a liuely Faith, learne and labour with our Apoſtle in this ſhort Race of your liues, ſtill to <hi>looke vnto Ieſus. In quo omnia habemus.</hi> In whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone wee haue all things neceſſarie to Saluation, as Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſayth; Whoſe bleſſed Birth, was and is our new Birth; whoſe Victorie ouer the Tempter, was our Triumph; his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, our Peace and quietneſſe; his Prayers, our Interceſſion; his Pouertie, our Riches; his Soares, our Salues; his Wounds, our Medicines; his Righteouſneſſe, our Merits; and laſtly, his Death, our Life.</p>
            <p>My ſecond and laſt vſe of this my laſt Inſtruction, raiſed from theſe laſt words: <hi>Looking to Ieſus.</hi> Is of admonition to warne vs all, in the Running of this our Religious Race, (wherein euery true Chriſtian is a Runner:) that we may ſo runne indeed, as to enioy the prize, which is Eternall life with Chriſt in Heauen, in our day of Death. Let vs now make Chriſt our onely Marke, our Copie, Goale, and Guide: both in beleeuing, and in liuing as wee ought to doe. So that
<pb facs="tcp:15807:22"/>firſt, if wee would know what we ought to beleeue, <hi>let vs looke to Ieſus:</hi> who is made vnto vs of God his Father, Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Righteouſneſſe, Sanctification, and Redemption. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. And who alone is both the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning, and the end, the firſt and the laſt of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22.13. There being none other Name giuen vnder Heauen, whereby wee can bee ſaued, but onely the Name of IESVS. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. Secondly, if wee would know how we ought for to liue, and leade our Liues heere, <hi>let vs looke vnto Ieſus.</hi> Firſt, for that the moſt Holy life of Ieſus, whiles heere hee liued and remayned vpon Earth, both was, and is, <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um virtutum perfectiſſima idea:</hi> The moſt perfect Patterne of all true Vertues. Inſomuch, that whereas <hi>Enoch</hi> is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſacred Scriptures for his Pietie: <hi>Abraham</hi> for his Faith, and Perſeuerance: <hi>Iob</hi> for his Patience: <hi>Iſaac</hi> for his Coeleſtiall meditation: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> for his Chaſtitie: <hi>Moſes</hi> for his Meekneſſe: <hi>Phinea</hi> for his Zeale: <hi>Samuel</hi> for his vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>Tobias</hi> for his Mercie: <hi>Daniel</hi> for his Prayers and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion: and laſtly, <hi>Salomon</hi> for his Wiſedome; Yet behold though wee put all theſe together, euen as a Cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, the onely example of this our <hi>Ieſus</hi> is in ſtead of them all. Theſe holy Men hauing all of them but a meaſure of Grace: whereas the Sonne of Man alone had Grace aboue meaſure.</p>
            <p>And therefore hee is ſtiled <hi>Sanctus Sanctorum,</hi> the Holie of Holies, as in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.3. No maruell, for as in the moſt Sacred place, was contayned the Golden Cenſer; the Arke of the Teſtament; the Golden Pot that contayned Manna; the Rod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> which being dead, budded againe; and the winges of the Cherubins ouerſhadowing the Mercie Seate. So in CHRIST alone, is contayned that Arke of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall Couenant, betwixt God and vs; together with the Cenſer, which is the acceptation of the Prayers of the Saints; and the Golden Pot, which contayneth the Manna; to wit, the bleſſed Sacrament: and <hi>Aarons</hi> dead Rodde that budded againe; which is the hope of our Reſurrection: and
<pb facs="tcp:15807:22"/>laſtly, the two Cherubins that looke face to face; which are the two Teſtaments, the Old and the New, looking to that one Mercie ſeate, which is, this our IESVS; Whom <hi>Eſay</hi> calleth the Prince of Peace. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Aggat,</hi> the deſire of the Nations. <hi>Aggai.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Malachi,</hi> the Sonne of Righteouſneſſe. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. And laſtly, the Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> IESVS. <hi>Math.</hi> 1.21. that is, a Sauiour: who alone ſhall ſaue all his people from their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, let vs looke vnto this our <hi>Ieſus,</hi> for that <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Chriſti actio noſtra est inſtitutio;</hi> Euery action of our Lord and Maſter CHRIST, it is our inſtruction. And therefore to whatſoeuer Chriſtian dutie, hee hath exhorted vs in his Word, as our principall Teacher. In the very ſame hee hath alſo gone before vs for our imitation, as a moſt perfect obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, euermore liuing as hee taught. In <hi>Math.</hi> 5.3. as he taught vs in his Word, to bee poore in Spirit. So in his life, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer poorer then hee; who became from being equall with his Father in Heauen, farre lower then the Angels; yea, a very ſcorne of men and out-caſt of the people? In <hi>Math.</hi> 11.29. as hee taught vs in Word, to bee meeke and lowly. So in deed, who euer more meeke then hee, who was as a Sheepe before the Shearer, not once opening his mouth? In <hi>Math.</hi> 5.4. as hee taught vs to Mourne and heartily to Lament. So who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed euer mourned and lamented, as hee did: for that as in <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7. In the dayes of his Fleſh, he offered vp prayers and ſupplications, with ſtrong Crying and Teares, vnto him that was able to faue him from Death? In <hi>Math.</hi> 5.6. as he taught vs to hunger, and thirſt after Righteouſneſſe. So in this, who euer hungred and thirſted more then hee, who gaue his Life for the Righteouſneſſe of many? Laſt of all, as in <hi>Math.</hi> 10.37. Hee hath taught vs in Word, to leaue all for his Loue. So firſt he left all for the Loue of vs, when he left his Kingdome and his Throne in Heauen. Thus you ſee, as hee taught vs by his Word, ſo was hee in like manner our Fore-runner by his Workes; ſtill leuelling and laying out vnto vs the way wherein wee ſhould walke, which leadeth vnto Life, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:15807:23"/>way if in this Life wee labour to make ours, then ſhall his joyes bee our joyes in the Life to come.</p>
            <p>Wherefore generally from hence forward, in all our ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and our doings, let vs euer looke vnto this our IESVS: ſo that when wee doe ſpeake, let vs thinke how hee hath ſpoken: and when wee keepe ſilence, let vs thinke of his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: and in all our Actions let vs looke to him for our Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſeeing that his whole life was an Inſtruction for our liues: who had Modeſtie in his Countenance, Grauitie in his Behauiour, Deliberation in his Speeches, Puritie in his Thoughts, and Righteouſneſſe in all his doings.</p>
            <p>When Mariners vpon the mayne Sea, doe want markes to direct them by in their courſe of ſayling, they then take their marke (which is the ſureſt) from the Heauens: in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for vs all that are Runners in this Race, our ſureſt marke to direct vs by, is to looke vp to IESVS, whoſe habitation is in Heauen: which will preſerue vs ſafely betwixt <hi>Silla,</hi> and <hi>Charibdis,</hi> Preſumption and Deſperation, all our whole journey, vnto the port of Paradice, whom truely to follow, as to know, is euerlaſting Life. Euery one of vs I know, would moſt willingly haue and enioy this Ieſus in the Life to come, and yet many of vs now make no Conſcience to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in this preſent Life. But let vs all aſſure our ſelues, that vnleſſe wee bee his Diſciples, and faithfull followers now, we ſhall neuer bee triumphant Chriſtians with him in his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And therefore this our IESVS, is <hi>Rubicundus &amp; Candidus,</hi> White and Ruddie, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. So muſt we alſo (beloued) be not onely Ruddie by the application of his Paſſion, but alſo White by the daily imitation of his moſt Sanctified life and conuerſation: knowing well, that as a Learned Father ſayth; <hi>Non ſolum Christi Paſſio est nostrum meritum, ſed etiam Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti actio ſit vitae nostrae exemplum.</hi> Not onely CHRIST his Paſſion is our Merit: but alſo his moſt Holy and Vertuous life muſt bee our Example. Who hath commanded vs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Sequimini me,</hi> Follow me. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.23.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:23"/>
            <p> It was ſayd of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that in his greateſt Attempts, hee vſed not the word of Authoritie, <hi>Ite,</hi> Goe yee, but after a better manner, and more louing: <hi>Eamus,</hi> Let vs goe. Which was moſt true in this our Maſter CHRIST before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who as wee finde euer led the way himſelfe before his Diſciples, in all Holineſſe of Life, in all Tryals and Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in all Conflicts and Temptations, which are heere wont to ariſe in the life of Man. And therefore our Apoſtle wils vs heere, <hi>To runne with Patience the Race that is ſet before vs, looking to Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which, that from henceforth wee may doe, let vs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore moſt carefully keepe and obſerue, theſe foure Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſteppes or degrees in this our Religious <hi>Race.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Mature,</hi> to begin betimes: for that as in <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.27. It is good for a man that hee beare the Lords yoake in his Youth. Secondly, <hi>Propere,</hi> To make haſt: for that <hi>Mora trahit periculum,</hi> Delayes are dangerous. Thirdly, <hi>Recte,</hi> To keepe on carefully in this way: for that as in <hi>Eſay</hi> 30.21. This is the way, walke in it: turne not aſide either to the right hand or to the left. And fourthly, <hi>Conſtanter,</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the Goales end: for that as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. Hee which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercommeth, and continueth vnto the End, ſhall not bee hurt of the ſecond Death.</p>
            <p>And theſe foure former Steps or Degrees, that in Running of this our appointed Race, wee may now the more happily and comfortably keepe and obſerue, wee muſt fully and faithfully reſolue with our owne ſelues, of theſe ſixe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and principall Points. Firſt, that wee haue neuer Runne farre enough heere. Secondly, that our onely ayme and marke, muſt bee this IESVS. Thirdly, that wee muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all our Ground that is behinde vs: that is, all thoſe ſteppes which wee haue trodden in. Fourthly, that wee muſt daily endeauour our ſelues to that which is before: which is to the practice of thoſe Chriſtian duties, that wee haue left vndone. Fiftly, that wee muſt caſt off all impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:15807:24"/>in this Race. And laſt of all, That when wee haue runne heere as faſt, and as farre as poſſibly we can, yet that our Reward and Crowne is in Heauen. To the which, our Lord IESVS bring vs all, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15807:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
